[
    {
        "question": "If the energy of the incident photon is less than the work function:",
        "choices": [
            "an electron will be ejected",
            "more than one electron will be ejected",
            "an electron will not be ejected",
            "less than one electron will be ejected"
        ],
        "answer": "an electron will not be ejected"
    },
    {
        "question": "For supersonic flow, the pressure of fluid must decrease as the fluid flow area of the duct",
        "choices": [
            "increases",
            "decreases",
            "remain the same",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
        "question": "Density in terms of viscosity is",
        "choices": [
            "kinematic viscosity / dynamic viscosity",
            "dynamic viscosity / kinematic viscosity",
            "kinematic viscosity x dynamic viscosity",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "dynamic viscosity / kinematic viscosity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Liquids and gases take the following characteristic(s) of their contents.",
        "choices": [
            "Volume",
            "Shape",
            "Shape and volume",
            "Neither shape nor volume"
        ],
        "answer": "Shape"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol finds use in manometers as",
        "choices": [
            "it provides suitable meniscus for the inclined tube",
            "its density being less can provide longer length for a pressure difference, thus more accuracy can be obtained",
            "A and B above are correct",
            "Cheap and easily available"
        ],
        "answer": "A and B above are correct"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about a Newtonian fluid is most accurate?",
        "choices": [
            "Shear stress is proportional to strain",
            "Viscosity is zero",
            "Shear stress is multi- valued",
            "Shear stress is proportional to rate of strain"
        ],
        "answer": "Shear stress is proportional to rate of strain"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal stress is the same in all directions at a point in fluid:",
        "choices": [
            "independent of the motion of one fluid layer relative to an adjacent layer",
            "when there is no motion of one fluid layer relative to an adjacent layer",
            "only if the fluid is frictionless",
            "only if fluid is frictionless and incompressible"
        ],
        "answer": "when there is no motion of one fluid layer relative to an adjacent layer"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of fluid pressure?",
        "choices": [
            "It is the same in all directions at a point in the fluid",
            "It acts normal to a surface",
            "It is a shear stress",
            "It is linear with depth"
        ],
        "answer": "It is a shear stress"
    },
    {
        "question": "The length of mercury column at a place at an altitude will change with respect to that at ground in;",
        "choices": [
            "a linear relation",
            "a parabolic relation",
            "will remain constant",
            "first slowly and then steeply"
        ],
        "answer": "first slowly and then steeply"
    },
    {
        "question": "All of the following dimensionless parameters are applicable to fluid flow problems except the _____",
        "choices": [
            "Reynolds number",
            "Froude number",
            "Mach number",
            "Biot number"
        ],
        "answer": "Biot number"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mass density of liquid (p) is given by which of the following?",
        "choices": [
            "p = Mass / volume",
            "p = metric slug /m²",
            "p = kg sec² / m⁴",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "question": "The speed of sound in all fluid is most closely related to all of the following properties except _______",
        "choices": [
            "compressibility",
            "density",
            "bulk modulus",
            "thermal conductivity"
        ],
        "answer": "thermal conductivity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under which condition, the specific weight of water is 1000 kg/m³?",
        "choices": [
            "at normal pressure of 760 mm",
            "at 4°C temperature",
            "at mean sea level",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "question": "All of the following can be characteristics of fluids except ________.",
        "choices": [
            "kinematic viscosity",
            "surface tension",
            "bulk modulus",
            "hysteresis"
        ],
        "answer": "hysteresis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following can be used to measure the flow of water in a pipe of diameter 3000 mm?",
        "choices": [
            "Venturimeter",
            "Rotameter",
            "Nozzle",
            "Pitot tube"
        ],
        "answer": "Pitot tube"
    },
    {
        "question": "The pressure at a given depth due to several immiscible liquids is:",
        "choices": [
            "the average of the individual pressures",
            "the sum of the individual pressures",
            "independent of the individual pressures",
            "unknown"
        ],
        "answer": "the sum of the individual pressures"
    },
    {
        "question": "The equation of continuity of flow is applicable if:",
        "choices": [
            "the flow is one dimensional",
            "the flow is steady",
            "the velocity is uniform over the cross - section",
            "all of the above conditions are together"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above conditions are together"
    },
    {
        "question": "Uniform flow takes place when:",
        "choices": [
            "conditions remain unchanged with time at any point",
            "rate of change of velocity of fluid is zero",
            "at every point the velocity vector is identical magnitude and direction for any given instant",
            "the change in transverse direction is zero"
        ],
        "answer": "at every point the velocity vector is identical magnitude and direction for any given instant"
    },
    {
        "question": "The continuity equation of an ideal fluid flow:",
        "choices": [
            "states that the net rate of in - flow into any small volume must be zero",
            "applies to irrotational flow only",
            "states that the energy remains constant along streamline",
            "states that energy is constant everywhere in the fluid"
        ],
        "answer": "states that energy is constant everywhere in the fluid"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pitot tube can be used to measure fluid velocity as described by the Bernoulli's equation and the relationship between:",
        "choices": [
            "kinetic energy and static pressure",
            "fluid pressure and height of the fluid",
            "fluid pressure and impact energy",
            "pressure and momentum"
        ],
        "answer": "kinetic energy and static pressure"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to avoid vaporization in the pipe line, the pipe line over the ridge is laid in such a way that it is not more than:",
        "choices": [
            "2.4 m above the hydraulic gradient",
            "6.4 m above the hydraulic gradient",
            "10.0 m above the hydraulic gradient",
            "5.0 above the hydraulic gradient"
        ],
        "answer": "6.4 m above the hydraulic gradient"
    },
    {
        "question": "The stream function is a useful parameter in describing ________",
        "choices": [
            "the conservation of mass",
            "the conservation of momentum",
            "the conservation of energy",
            "the equation of state"
        ],
        "answer": "the conservation of mass"
    },
    {
        "question": "For high speed flows, the potential energy of the fluids are:",
        "choices": [
            "positive",
            "negative",
            "negligible",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "negligible"
    },
    {
        "question": "McLeod gauge used for low pressure measurement operates on the principle of ________",
        "choices": [
            "Gas law",
            "Boyle's law",
            "Charles law",
            "Pascal's law"
        ],
        "answer": "Boyle's law"
    },
    {
        "question": "A Kaplan turbine is",
        "choices": [
            "a high head mixed flow turbine",
            "an impulse turbine, inward flow",
            "a reaction turbine, outward flow",
            "low head axial flow turbine"
        ],
        "answer": "low head axial flow turbine"
    },
    {
        "question": "The most common method for calculating frictional energy loss for laminar flowing fluids in noncircular pipes is:",
        "choices": [
            "the Darcy equation",
            "the Hagan - Poisevill equation",
            "the Hazen - Williams equation",
            "the Swamee - Jin equation"
        ],
        "answer": "the Darcy equation"
    },
    {
        "question": "The parameter f in the expression for head-loss is",
        "choices": [
            "the fraction of flow that is totally turbulent",
            "the Darcy friction factor",
            "the height of the roughness scale in turbulent flow",
            "the static coefficient of friction"
        ],
        "answer": "the Darcy friction factor"
    },
    {
        "question": "Friction factor for both laminar and turbulent flows can be found plotted in a",
        "choices": [
            "steam table",
            "psychrometric chart",
            "Moody diagram D.",
            "Mollier diagram"
        ],
        "answer": "Moody diagram D."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is relative velocity?",
        "choices": [
            "The difference between two velocities",
            "Average velocity",
            "Sum of two velocities",
            "Vector difference of two velocities"
        ],
        "answer": "Vector difference of two velocities"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the highest head?",
        "choices": [
            "33 inch Hg",
            "31.0 ft. water",
            "1.013 kg kg/cm²",
            "75.0 cm of Hg"
        ],
        "answer": "33 inch Hg"
    },
    {
        "question": "For stable equilibrium of floating body its metacenter should lie:",
        "choices": [
            "below the center of gravity",
            "below the center of buoyancy",
            "above the center of buoyancy",
            "above the center of gravity"
        ],
        "answer": "above the center of gravity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Center of pressure on an inclined plane lies ______",
        "choices": [
            "at the centroid",
            "above the centroid",
            "below the centroid",
            "at metacenter"
        ],
        "answer": "below the centroid"
    },
    {
        "question": "The line of action of the buoyant forces always acts through the centroid of the ________",
        "choices": [
            "submerged body",
            "volume of the floating body",
            "volume of the fluid vertically above the body",
            "displaced volume of the fluid"
        ],
        "answer": "displaced volume of the fluid"
    },
    {
        "question": "The hydraulic grade line of a pipeline denotes which of the following?",
        "choices": [
            "Total energy",
            "Pressure energy",
            "Potential energy",
            "The sum of pressure energy and potential energy"
        ],
        "answer": "The sum of pressure energy and potential energy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The energy grade line of a pipeline denotes which of the following",
        "choices": [
            "Total energy",
            "Pressure energy",
            "Potential energy",
            "The sum of pressure energy and potential energy"
        ],
        "answer": "Total energy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The presence of friction in the energy grade line will always cause the line to slope",
        "choices": [
            "down in the direction of the flow",
            "upward in the direction of the flow",
            "level (no slope)",
            "there is no effect of friction on the energy grad line"
        ],
        "answer": "down in the direction of the flow"
    },
    {
        "question": "The pitot tube is a device used for measurement of",
        "choices": [
            "pressure",
            "flow",
            "velocity",
            "discharge"
        ],
        "answer": "velocity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hydrometer is used to find out",
        "choices": [
            "specific gravity of liquids",
            "specific gravity of solids",
            "specific gravity of gases",
            "relative humidity"
        ],
        "answer": "specific gravity of liquids"
    },
    {
        "question": "The fluid forces taken into consideration in the Navier Stokes equation are:",
        "choices": [
            "gravity, pressure and viscous",
            "gravity, pressure and turbulent",
            "pressure, viscous and turbulent",
            "gravity, viscous and turbulent"
        ],
        "answer": "gravity, pressure and viscous"
    },
    {
        "question": "Permissible velocity of water flowing through concrete tunnel, is generally",
        "choices": [
            "4 - 5 m/s",
            "10 - 12 m/s",
            "13 - 16 m/s",
            "20 m/s"
        ],
        "answer": "4 - 5 m/s"
    },
    {
        "question": "Orifice refers to an opening",
        "choices": [
            "with closed perimeter and of regular form through which water flows",
            "with prolonged sides having length of 2 to 3 diameters of opening in thick wall",
            "with partially full flow",
            "in hydraulic structure with regulation provision"
        ],
        "answer": "in hydraulic structure with regulation provision"
    },
    {
        "question": "The value of coefficient of discharge in comparison to coefficient of velocity is found to be _______",
        "choices": [
            "more",
            "less",
            "same",
            "more/less depending on flow"
        ],
        "answer": "less"
    },
    {
        "question": "Weir refers to an opening",
        "choices": [
            "having closed perimeter and of regular form through which water flows",
            "having prolonged sides with length of 2 to 3 diameters of opening in thick wall",
            "having partially full flow",
            "in hydraulic structure with regulation provision"
        ],
        "answer": "having partially full flow"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following parameters determine the friction factor of turbulent flow in a rough pipe?",
        "choices": [
            "Froude number and relative roughness",
            "Froude number and Mach. number",
            "Reynolds number and relative roughness",
            "Mach number and relative roughness"
        ],
        "answer": "Reynolds number and relative roughness"
    },
    {
        "question": "Power transmitted through a pipe is maximum when the loss of head due to friction is :",
        "choices": [
            "one - half of the total head supplied",
            "one - third of the total head supplied",
            "one - fourth of the total head supplied",
            "equal to the total head supplied"
        ],
        "answer": "one - third of the total head supplied"
    },
    {
        "question": "In a nozzle if back pressure is same as inlet pressure; then ______",
        "choices": [
            "no flow takes place",
            "maximum flow takes place",
            "flow becomes subsonic in diverging section",
            "flow becomes supersonic in converging as well as supersonic section"
        ],
        "answer": "no flow takes place"
    },
    {
        "question": "The flow on two sides of a normal shock wave is called",
        "choices": [
            "sonic",
            "sub- sonic",
            "supersonic",
            "supersonic on one side and sub - sonic on the other side"
        ],
        "answer": "supersonic on one side and sub - sonic on the other side"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the basic of Bernoulli's law for fluid flow?",
        "choices": [
            "Continuity equation",
            "Principle of conservation of energy",
            "Fourier's law",
            "Principle of conservation of mass"
        ],
        "answer": "Principle of conservation of energy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of fluid pressure?",
        "choices": [
            "It is a shear stress",
            "It is the same in all directions at a point in the fluid",
            "It acts normal to a surface",
            "It is linear with depth"
        ],
        "answer": "It is a shear stress"
    },
    {
        "question": "Refers to the compressibility of a fluid, the fractional change in fluid volume per unit change in fluid.",
        "choices": [
            "Viscosity",
            "Bulk modulus",
            "Density",
            "Pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Pressure"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pitot tube can be used to measure fluid velocity as described by the Bernoulli equation: and the relationship between:",
        "choices": [
            "kinetic energy and static pressure",
            "fluid pressure and static pressure.",
            "fluid pressure and impact energy",
            "pressure and momentum"
        ],
        "answer": "kinetic energy and static pressure"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ratio of the area to the wetted perimeter is known as _______.",
        "choices": [
            "flow factor",
            "hydraulic radius",
            "Kutter's C",
            "value of k in Darcy - Weisbach formula"
        ],
        "answer": "hydraulic radius"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the coefficient of contraction?",
        "choices": [
            "The ratio of the area of vena contracta to the area of the orifice",
            "The ratio of actual discharge to the theoretical discharge",
            "The ratio of the actual velocity to the theoretical velocity",
            "The ratio of the effective head to the actual head"
        ],
        "answer": "The ratio of the area of vena contracta to the area of the orifice"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where is vena contracta most likely located?",
        "choices": [
            "At the orifice",
            "At a distance approximately ½ the diameter of the orifice",
            "At a distance approximately equal to the diameter of the orifice",
            "At a distance approximately twice the diameter of the orifice"
        ],
        "answer": "At a distance approximately ½ the diameter of the orifice"
    },
    {
        "question": "A substance that is able to flow and yields to any force tending to change its shape without changing its volume such as water and air.",
        "choices": [
            "Fluid",
            "Flux",
            "Gas oil",
            "Water gas"
        ],
        "answer": "Fluid"
    },
    {
        "question": "The velocity of a fluid particle at the center of the pipe section is ________.",
        "choices": [
            "maximum",
            "minimum",
            "average",
            "logarithmic average"
        ],
        "answer": "maximum"
    },
    {
        "question": "For supersonic flow, the pressure of fluid must increase as the fluid flow area of the duct:",
        "choices": [
            "increases",
            "decreases",
            "constant",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "decreases"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is incorrect statement regarding apparent shear forces.",
        "choices": [
            "It can never be found in frictionless fluid regardless of its motion",
            "It can never be found when the fluid is at rest",
            "It depends upon cohesive forces",
            "It may occur owing to cohesion when the fluid is at rest"
        ],
        "answer": "It may occur owing to cohesion when the fluid is at rest"
    },
    {
        "question": "The time required for half a quantity of radioactive particles to decay (disintegrate) is called its _____",
        "choices": [
            "average life",
            "median life",
            "time constant",
            "half time"
        ],
        "answer": "half time"
    },
    {
        "question": "SI unit of viscosity is :",
        "choices": [
            "10 times poise",
            "9.81 times poise",
            "1 / 9.81 times poise",
            "1/ 10 times poise"
        ],
        "answer": "10 times poise"
    },
    {
        "question": "For computation convenience, fluids are usually classed as :",
        "choices": [
            "rotational or irrotational",
            "real or ideal",
            "laminar or turbulent",
            "Newtonian or non-Newtonian"
        ],
        "answer": "real or ideal"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not a dimensionless parameter?",
        "choices": [
            "Kinetic viscosity",
            "Weber number",
            "Darcy Weisbach friction factor",
            "Froude number"
        ],
        "answer": "Kinetic viscosity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of real fluids?",
        "choices": [
            "Finite viscosity",
            "Non - uniform velocity distributions",
            "Compressibility",
            "Experience of eddy currents and turbulence"
        ],
        "answer": "Experience of eddy currents and turbulence"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not the mass density of water?",
        "choices": [
            "62.5 Ibm/ft³",
            "100 kg/m³",
            "1 g/cm³",
            "1 kg/L"
        ],
        "answer": "100 kg/m³"
    },
    {
        "question": "The upper critical Reynolds number for pipe flow is:",
        "choices": [
            "of no practical importance to designers",
            "always used to design pipes for strength",
            "the number at which turbulent flow changes over to laminar flow",
            "the number at which laminar flow changes into turbulent flow"
        ],
        "answer": "of no practical importance to designers"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about gauge pressure is most correct? Gauge pressure are measured relative to ______.",
        "choices": [
            "atmospheric pressure",
            "a vacuum",
            "each other",
            "the surface"
        ],
        "answer": "atmospheric pressure"
    },
    {
        "question": "The volumetric change of the fluid caused by a resistance is called _________",
        "choices": [
            "volumetric strain",
            "volumetric index",
            "compressibility",
            "adhesion"
        ],
        "answer": "adhesion"
    },
    {
        "question": "Compressibility of a fluid relates the fractional change in fluid volume per unit change in fluid.",
        "choices": [
            "temperature",
            "density",
            "pressure",
            "viscosity"
        ],
        "answer": "pressure"
    },
    {
        "question": "Property of a fluid whereby its own molecules are attracted is known as _______",
        "choices": [
            "adhesion",
            "cohesion",
            "surface tension",
            "viscosity"
        ],
        "answer": "cohesion"
    },
    {
        "question": "The term subsonic flow refers to a flowing gas with a speed:",
        "choices": [
            "less than the local speed of sound",
            "equal to the speed of sound",
            "greater than the speed of sound",
            "much greater than the speed of sound"
        ],
        "answer": "less than the local speed of sound"
    },
    {
        "question": "The pressure at a point in a fluid will not be same in all the directions if the fluid is:",
        "choices": [
            "viscous",
            "viscous and static",
            "inviscous and in motion",
            "viscous and is in motion"
        ],
        "answer": "viscous and is in motion"
    },
    {
        "question": "The statement that \"the hydrostatic pressure a fluid exerts on an immersed object or on container walls is a function only of fluid depth\" is",
        "choices": [
            "the perfect gas law",
            "D'Alembert's paradox",
            "the hydrostatic paradox",
            "Boyle's law"
        ],
        "answer": "the hydrostatic paradox"
    },
    {
        "question": "Bernoulli's equation is s/an _______",
        "choices": [
            "momentum equation",
            "conservation of energy equation",
            "conservation of mass equation",
            "equation of state"
        ],
        "answer": "conservation of energy equation"
    },
    {
        "question": "An ideal fluid is one that :",
        "choices": [
            "is very viscous",
            "obeys Netwon's law of viscosity",
            "is assumed in problems in conduit flow",
            "is frictionless and incompressible"
        ],
        "answer": "is frictionless and incompressible"
    },
    {
        "question": "The relationship between pressure and altitude in the atmosphere is given by the:",
        "choices": [
            "perfect gas law",
            "conservation of mass",
            "barometric height relationship",
            "first law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "barometric height relationship"
    },
    {
        "question": "The fact the buoyant force on a floating object equal to the weight of the water displaced is:",
        "choices": [
            "Bernoulli's law",
            "Archimedes' principle",
            "The law of diminishing returns",
            "The conservation of mass"
        ],
        "answer": "Archimedes' principle"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following terms does not appear in the steady flow energy equation (the extended Bernoulli's equation)?",
        "choices": [
            "Kinetic energy",
            "Potential energy",
            "Friction losses",
            "Hysteresis losses"
        ],
        "answer": "Hysteresis losses"
    },
    {
        "question": "Neglecting the forces due to inertia, gravity and frictional resistance, the design of a channel can be made by comparing",
        "choices": [
            "Weber number",
            "Reynolds number",
            "Froude's number",
            "Prant'l number"
        ],
        "answer": "Froude's number"
    },
    {
        "question": "The difference between stagnation pressure and total pressure is :",
        "choices": [
            "due to height difference",
            "due to fluid kinetic energy",
            "none of the terms are interchangeable",
            "important only in supersonic flow"
        ],
        "answer": "none of the terms are interchangeable"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fully turbulent flow in a pipe is characterized by all of the following except:",
        "choices": [
            "a parabolic velocity profile",
            "a momentum exchange due to fluid masses rather than molecules",
            "a maximum velocity at the fluid center line",
            "a 1/7 velocity profile"
        ],
        "answer": "a parabolic velocity profile"
    },
    {
        "question": "The laminar friction factor of fluid flowing through a pipe is a function of all of the following except:",
        "choices": [
            "fluid velocity",
            "pipe diameter",
            "pipe roughness",
            "Reynolds number"
        ],
        "answer": "pipe roughness"
    },
    {
        "question": "The continuity equation is applicable to:",
        "choices": [
            "viscous unviscous fluids",
            "compressibility of fluids",
            "conservation of mass",
            "steady unsteady flow"
        ],
        "answer": "conservation of mass"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rise or fall of head 'h' in a capillary tube of diameter 'd' and liquid surface tension 's' and specific weight 'w' is given by:",
        "choices": [
            "4s/wd",
            "4ds/w",
            "4wd/s",
            "4ws/d"
        ],
        "answer": "4s/wd"
    },
    {
        "question": "The study of the practical laws of fluid flow and the resistance of open pipes and channels.",
        "choices": [
            "fluid mechanics",
            "hydraulics",
            "aerodynamics",
            "thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "hydraulics"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following turbine is different from the others?",
        "choices": [
            "Fourneyron turbine",
            "Francis turbine",
            "Kaplan turbine",
            "Pelton wheel"
        ],
        "answer": "Pelton wheel"
    },
    {
        "question": "Running away speed of a Pelton wheel gives:",
        "choices": [
            "actual operating speed",
            "no load speed",
            "full load speed",
            "no load speed when governor mechanism fails"
        ],
        "answer": "no load speed when governor mechanism fails"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following turbine is different from the others?",
        "choices": [
            "Pelton wheel",
            "Banki turbine",
            "Jonval turbine",
            "Kaplan turbine"
        ],
        "answer": "Kaplan turbine"
    },
    {
        "question": "The characteristic length of the Reynold's number used to calculate the friction in noncircular full running pipes is based on the ________.",
        "choices": [
            "run length",
            "pipe length",
            "hydraulic diameter (the equivalent diameter)",
            "wetted circumference"
        ],
        "answer": "hydraulic diameter (the equivalent diameter)"
    },
    {
        "question": "The hydraulic radius of noncircular pipe is:",
        "choices": [
            "the square root of the flow area",
            "the ratio of the area to the wetted perimeter",
            "the radius of a pipe of equivalent area",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "the ratio of the area to the wetted perimeter"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Darcy equation can be used for all liquids and flows except:",
        "choices": [
            "water",
            "alcohol",
            "gasoline",
            "air flowing supersonically"
        ],
        "answer": "air flowing supersonically"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Hazen - Williams formula for head loss due to friction is based upon :",
        "choices": [
            "A rigorous mathematical derivation",
            "empirical data",
            "semi - empirical analysis",
            "screndipity"
        ],
        "answer": "empirical data"
    },
    {
        "question": "The extended Bernoulli equation includes all of the following terms except:",
        "choices": [
            "potential energy",
            "kinetic energy",
            "nuclear energy",
            "friction losses"
        ],
        "answer": "nuclear energy"
    },
    {
        "question": "An equipotential line is one that:",
        "choices": [
            "has no velocity component tangent to it",
            "has uniformly varying dynamic pressure",
            "has no velocity component normal to it",
            "exists in case of rotational flow"
        ],
        "answer": "has no velocity component tangent to it"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the use of a Hydraulic jump?",
        "choices": [
            "increase the flow rate",
            "reduce the flow rate",
            "reduce the velocity of flow",
            "reduce the energy of flow"
        ],
        "answer": "reduce the energy of flow"
    },
    {
        "question": "What do you call the lowest portion to storage basin from where the water is not drawn?",
        "choices": [
            "bottom storage",
            "sub soil storage",
            "spring reserve",
            "dead storage"
        ],
        "answer": "dead storage"
    },
    {
        "question": "The presence of friction in the hydraulic grade line will always cause the line to slope",
        "choices": [
            "down in the direction of the flow",
            "upward in the direction of the flow",
            "level (no slope)",
            "there is no effect of friction on the energy grade line"
        ],
        "answer": "down in the direction of the flow"
    },
    {
        "question": "The presence of a minor loss in the energy grade line will cause the line to slope :",
        "choices": [
            "down in the direction of the flow",
            "upward in the direction of the flow",
            "vertically downward",
            "there is no effect of friction on the energy grade line"
        ],
        "answer": "down in the direction of the flow"
    },
    {
        "question": "What do you call the pressure which the fluid exerts on an immersed object or container walls?",
        "choices": [
            "Normal pressure",
            "Standard liquid pressure",
            "Hydrostatic pressure",
            "Gage pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydrostatic pressure"
    },
    {
        "question": "Viscosity for a fluid is defined as the constant proportionality between shear stress and what other variable?",
        "choices": [
            "The spatial derivative of velocity",
            "The time derivative of pressure",
            "The time derivative of density",
            "The spatial derivative of density"
        ],
        "answer": "The spatial derivative of velocity"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the classification of the fluid flow if the fluid travels parallel to the adjacent layers and the paths of the individual particles do not cross each other?",
        "choices": [
            "Steady flow",
            "Laminar flow",
            "Uniform flow",
            "Turbulent flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Laminar flow"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following refers to the measure of a fluid's sensitivity to changes in viscosity with changes in temperature?",
        "choices": [
            "Viscosity index",
            "Coefficient of viscosity",
            "Viscosity ratio",
            "Viscosity factor"
        ],
        "answer": "Viscosity index"
    },
    {
        "question": "If the Mach number is greater than 1 but lesser than 5, what is the standard classification of the travel?",
        "choices": [
            "Transonic travel",
            "Subsonic travel",
            "Hypersonic travel",
            "Supersonic travel"
        ],
        "answer": "Supersonic travel"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is measured by a Pitot tube?",
        "choices": [
            "Volumetric discharge",
            "Mass flow",
            "Pressure",
            "Velocity"
        ],
        "answer": "Velocity"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the difference between the energy grade line and the hydraulic grade line?",
        "choices": [
            "potential energy",
            "pressure energy",
            "kinetic energy",
            "friction losses"
        ],
        "answer": "kinetic energy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Kinetic energy is not neglected in calculations of:",
        "choices": [
            "high speed flow",
            "low speed flow",
            "steady flow",
            "equilibrium flow"
        ],
        "answer": "high speed flow"
    },
    {
        "question": "Discharge losses through orifice are due to;",
        "choices": [
            "friction losses",
            "minor losses",
            "both friction and minor losses",
            "pressure losses"
        ],
        "answer": "both friction and minor losses"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is considered as an important parameter in the study of compressible flow?",
        "choices": [
            "speed of fluid",
            "speed of sound",
            "speed of light",
            "speed of fluid flow"
        ],
        "answer": "speed of sound"
    },
    {
        "question": "Is the velocity at which an infinitesimal small pressure wave travels through a medium.",
        "choices": [
            "Subsonic velocity",
            "Hypersonic velocity",
            "Sonic velocity",
            "Monatomic velocity"
        ],
        "answer": "Sonic velocity"
    },
    {
        "question": "It is the ratio of the actual velocity of the fluid to the velocity of sound.",
        "choices": [
            "Mach number",
            "Froude number",
            "Sonic number",
            "Euler number"
        ],
        "answer": "Mach number"
    },
    {
        "question": "The flow is called sonic when Mach number is:",
        "choices": [
            "equal to 1",
            "less than 1",
            "more than 1",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "equal to 1"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following flow is sub - sonic when Mach no. is:",
        "choices": [
            "greater than 1",
            "less than 1",
            "more than 1",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "less than 1"
    },
    {
        "question": "The flow is supersonic when Mach no. is:",
        "choices": [
            "greater than zero",
            "less than 1",
            "greater than 1",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "greater than 1"
    },
    {
        "question": "The flow is transonic when",
        "choices": [
            "M = O",
            "M < 1",
            "M > 1",
            "M = 1"
        ],
        "answer": "M = 1"
    },
    {
        "question": "The pressure decreases as the temperature and velocity increases while the fluid velocity and Mach number:",
        "choices": [
            "increases",
            "decreases",
            "remains constant",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Mach number is unity or one at the location of smallest flow area, called the :",
        "choices": [
            "decreasing are",
            "throat",
            "increasing area",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "throat"
    },
    {
        "question": "What happens to the velocity of fluid after passing the throat although the flow area",
        "choices": [
            "increases rapidly",
            "decreases rapidly",
            "remains constant",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "increases rapidly"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is an example of a Newtonian fluid?",
        "choices": [
            "Motor oils",
            "Gas",
            "Paints",
            "Clay slurries"
        ],
        "answer": "Gas"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the critical pressure of water ?",
        "choices": [
            "150 kg/cm³",
            "less than 200 kg/cm²",
            "more than 200 kg/cm²",
            "100 kg/cm²"
        ],
        "answer": "more than 200 kg/cm²"
    },
    {
        "question": "The volumetric change of the fluid caused by a resistance is called :",
        "choices": [
            "volumetric change",
            "volumetric index",
            "compressibility",
            "adhesion"
        ],
        "answer": "adhesion"
    },
    {
        "question": "The energy of a fluid flowing at any section in a pipeline is a function of:",
        "choices": [
            "velocity of flow only",
            "pressure only",
            "height above a chosen datum, density, internal energy, pressure and velocity of flow",
            "pressure, height above a chosen datum, velocity of flow, density of fluid"
        ],
        "answer": "height above a chosen datum, density, internal energy, pressure and velocity of flow"
    },
    {
        "question": "If the fluid travels parallel to the adjacent layers and the paths of individual particles do not cross, the fluid is said to be:",
        "choices": [
            "turbulent",
            "critical",
            "dynamic",
            "laminar"
        ],
        "answer": "laminar"
    },
    {
        "question": "Center of pressure on an inclined plane lies:",
        "choices": [
            "at the centroid",
            "above the centroid",
            "below the centroid",
            "at the metacenter"
        ],
        "answer": "below the centroid"
    },
    {
        "question": "At any instant, if the number of particles passing ever cross - section of the stream is the same, the flow is said to be:",
        "choices": [
            "steady flow",
            "uniform flow",
            "continuous flow",
            "laminar flow"
        ],
        "answer": "steady flow"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ratio of cross-sectional area of flow to the wetted perimeter is:",
        "choices": [
            "hydraulic lead",
            "hydraulic section",
            "hydraulic mean depth",
            "hydraulic gradient"
        ],
        "answer": "hydraulic mean depth"
    },
    {
        "question": "If A is the cross-sectional area of the flow and Pw is the wetted perimeter of a pipe, then what is the hydraulic depth. Hd ?",
        "choices": [
            "Pw - A",
            "Pw / A",
            "A / Pw",
            "Pw x A"
        ],
        "answer": "A / Pw"
    },
    {
        "question": "If Q is the volume in gallon; D is height or elevation in ft, and m is weight in Ibs per gallon , what is the desired energy to lift the water from lower to higher elevation ?",
        "choices": [
            "E = mD/Q",
            "E = mDQ",
            "E = mQ/D",
            "E = QD/m"
        ],
        "answer": "E = mDQ"
    },
    {
        "question": "The flow of the convergent section of a nozzle is always subsonic. If the flow is subsonic then the Mach number is:",
        "choices": [
            "greater than unity",
            "less than unity",
            "near unity",
            "unity"
        ],
        "answer": "less than unity"
    }
]